A Finding Aid to the Nancy Drysdale Gallery Records, 1971-1996, in the Archives of American Art AAA.nancdryg
Archives of American Art
Nancy Drysdale Gallery records
1971-1996
AAA.nancdryg
Archives of American Art
9 Linear feet
The records of the Nancy Drysdale Gallery measure 9.0 linear feet and span the years 1971 to 1996. The bulk of the collection comprises artist files that document the gallery's relations with 67 artists, many of whom were represented by the gallery.
Nancy Drysdale Gallery
Historical Note
When colleague Max Protech moved to New York City in 1976, his gallery at 2151 P Street, N.W., Washington, D.C., became the Protech-McIntosh Gallery under his successor, Cincinnati dealer, Nancy McIntosh Drysdale. Drysdale then moved the gallery to 406 7th Street, N.W., and changed the name to the McIntosh/Drysdale Gallery. Several years later, Drysdale vacated the 7th Street address and operated as a private dealer before opening the Nancy Drysdale Gallery at 2103 O Street, N.W., in 1991.
Scope and Content Note
This collection measures 9.0 linear feet and dates from 1971 to 1996. The bulk of the collection comprises artist files that document the gallery's relationships with 67 artists, many of whom were represented, or whose work was handled by, the gallery. In addition to artist files, the collection contains exhibition files, printed material, and publishers files.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as four series reflecting the original arrangement imposed by the Gallery.
Series 1: Group Exhibition Files, 1978-1994 (Box 1, 0.5 linear ft.)
Series 2: Fine Art Publishers Files, 1972-1995 (Boxes 1-2, 1.5 linear ft.)
Series 3: Artist Files, 1971-1996 (Boxes 2-9, 7 linear ft.)
Series 4: Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1993-1994 (Box 9, 1 folder)
Provenance
The records of the Nancy Drysdale Gallery were donated to the Archives of American Art by Nancy Drysdale in 1997.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for resesarch. Use requires an appointment.
Bartlett, Jennifer, 1941-; Brook Alexander Editions; Burton, Scott; Christenberry, William, 1936-; Clapsaddle, Jerry, 1941-; Crown Point Press; Drysdale, Nancy McIntosh, 1931-; Fuller, R. Buckminster (Richard Buckminster), 1895-; Gilliam, Sam; Kainen, Jacob; Katz, Alex, 1927-; LeWitt, Sol, 1928-2007; Mangold, Robert, 1937-; Puryear, Martin, 1941-; Scully, Sean, 1945-; Sonfist, Alan; Tracy, Michael, 1943-; Truitt, Anne, 1921-2004; Tyler Graphics, Ltd; Wegman, William; Zakanitch, Robert, 1935-; Art galleries, Commercial--Washington (D.C.); Art, Modern--20th century--Washington (D.C.); Artists--Washington (D.C.); Drawings; Interviews; Photographs; Slides (photographs)
- Group Exhibition Files, 1978-1994; Series 1; (0.5 linear ft.)
  Scope and Contents note
  This series documents twelve group exhibitions mounted at the Nancy Drysdale Gallery. Files may include consignment records; lists of artwork to be exhibited, some with prices; photographs and transparencies of artwork and exhibition installations; announcements, catalogs, and other printed material concerning the exhibitions; artist resumes; notes; and letters from artists including Jane Kaufman, Joyce Kozloff, Richard Pettibon, Larry Rivers, Kay Rosen, and Miriam Schapiro.
  Arrangement note
  The series is arranged chronologcially.
  - The Minimal Image, March 1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Art and Architecture, Space and Structure, January - February 1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Decorative Image, March 7 - April 2, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
    (Includes letters from artists Jane Kaufman, Joyce Kozloff, and Miriam Schapiro)
  - Small Bronzes, April 12 - May 14, [1983] (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Five Texas Artists, March 5 - April 12, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Investigations, May 15 - June 18, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    (Includes a letter from Richard Pettibon)
  - The Spectre of Saturation, March 6 - April 4, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Intimate Environments, October 20 - November 14, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Tsar Wars, [1911] (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Surveillance, October 8 - November 7, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Money/Politics/Sex, September - October, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    (Includes a letter from Larry Rivers and a letter from Kay Rosen)
  - Etchings and Aquatints, March 19 - April 16, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Fine Art Publishers' Files, 1972-1995; Series 2; (1.5 linear ft.)
  This series contains letters, price lists, photographs and transparencies of artwork, and printed material concerning the printing of editions of original artwork by 46 fine art publishing companies including Brook Alexander Editions, Crown Point Press, and Tyler Graphics, Ltd.
  The series is arranged alphabetically by publisher.
  - Baron/Boisante Editions, 1987-1992 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Berghoff-Cowden Editions, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    (Contains price list for work by Robert Zakanitch and George Sugarman)
  - Bethesda Art Gallery, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Brook Alexander Editions, 1981-1991 (Box 1, Folder 17-20)
  - Castelli Graphics, 1979-1993 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Chalk and Vermilion, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Crown Point Press, 1977-1995 (Box 1, Folder 23-21)
  - Cynthia Drennon Fine Arts Resources, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Daniel Elias Editions, 1992-1994 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Diane Villani Editions, 1986-1992 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Edition Deger, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Editions Mourlot, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Edition Schellmann, 1986-1991 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Galerie Lelong, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Garner Tullis, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    (Contains letter and publication announcement concerning Sean Scully)
  - Gemini G.E.L., 1977-1995 (Box 1, Folder 33-41)
  - Holly Solomon Editions, undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Hugh Lauter Levin Associates, Inc., 1984 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - I.C. Editions, Inc., 1993 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Jim Kempner Fine Art, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Limestone Press, undated (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Marlborough Graphics, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    (Contains a price list concerning artwork by Alex Katz)
  - Multiples, Inc., 1973-1992 (Box 1, Folder 48-49)
  - Pace Prints, 1990-1993 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Parasol Press, 1990-1994 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Permanent Press, 1990-1993 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Petersburg Press, Inc., 1976-1992 (Box 2, Folder 4-9)
  - Petra Holtzman Multiples, Ltd., 1993 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Richard Anderson Fine Art, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Robert Brown Gallery, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Robert Jackson Fine Arts, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Ronald Feldman Fine Arts, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Segura Publishing Company, Inc., 1994 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Shark's, Inc., 1988-1994 (Box 2, Folder 16-18)
  - Shirley Cerf, 1991-1992 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Simca Prints, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Smith Anderson Editions, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Solo Gallery, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Sonnabend Sundell Editions, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Styria Studio, Inc., 1981 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Sullivan Goss Books and Prints, Ltd., undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Tandem Press, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Tyler Graphics, Ltd., 1972-1995 (Box 2, Folder 27-33)
  - University of New Mexico Press, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Vermillion Editions, Ltd., 1983-1991 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - William K. Greiner, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Artist Files, 1971-1996; Series 3; (7 linear ft.)
  This series forms the bulk of the collection and concerns 67 artists including Jennifer Bartlett, Scott Burton, William Christenberry, Jerry Clapsaddle, Buckminster Fuller, Sam Gilliam, Jacob Kainen, Alex Katz, Sol Lewitt, Robert Mangold, Martin Puryear, Sean Scully, Alan Sonfist, Michael Tracy, Anne Truitt, William Wegman, and Robert Zakanitch. Many were represented/sold by the Gallery. The bulk of the material consists of photographs and transparencies of artwork and installations, and printed material such as clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, but the files also contain resumes, gallery correspondence, letters from artists, photographs of artists, and notes.
  The series is arranged alphabetically by artist.
  - Carl Andre, 1975-1980 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Dotty Attie, 1980-1983 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    (Contains a letter from Attie)
  - Alice Aycock, 1971-1986 (Box 2, Folder 39-44)
    (Contains a letter from Aycock)
  - Alice Aycock, 1971-1976 (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
  - Jennifer Bartlett, 1977-1994 (Box 3, Folder 4-14)
  - J. S. G. Boggs, 1990-1996 (Box 3, Folder 15-19)
  - Jonathan Borofsky, 1976-1985 (Box 3, Folder 20-22)
  - Scott Burton, 1976-1990 (Box 3, Folder 23-32)
    (Includes 3 letters and a drawing by Burton)
  - Sophie Calle, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Peter Campus, 1974-1991 (Box 3, Folder 34-36)
  - William Christenberry, 1991-1996 (Box 3, Folder 37-42)
  - Jerry Clapsaddle, 1981-1989 (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
  - Jud Fine, 1972-1982 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Joel Fisher, 1975-1995 (Box 4, Folder 5-7)
    (Includes 2 letters from Fisher)
  - Richard Fleischner, 1977-1995 (Box 4, Folder 8-15)
  - Buckminster Fuller, 1976-1977 (Box 4, Folder 16-17)
    (Includes a photograph of Fuller)
  - Sam Gilliam, 1975-1993 (Box 4, Folder 18-30)
    (Includes a photograph of Gillam)
  - Jan Groover, 1980-1993 (Box 4, Folder 31-33)
  - Brower Hatcher, 1973-1993 (Box 5, Folder 1-6)
  - Willie Heeks, 1986-1995 (Box 5, Folder 7-12)
    (Includes 2 letters from Heeks)
  - Bryan Hunt, 1986-1989 (Box 5, Folder 13-15)
  - Jacob Kainen, 1978-1995 (Box 5, Folder 16-28)
    (Includes interview transcripts, 2 letters from Kainen, and 14 photographs of Kainen)
  - Alex Katz, 1979-1996 (Box 5, Folder 29-35)
  - Elizabeth King, 1986-1995 (Box 5, Folder 36-43)
    (Includes 4 letters from King)
  - Joyce Kozloff, 1977-1995 (Box 6, Folder 1-8)
    (Includes 5 letters from Kozloff)
  - Louise Lawler, 1985-1990 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Catherine Lee, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    (Includes a letter from Lee)
  - Sol Lewitt, 1974-1995 (Box 6, Folder 11-15)
    (Includes a letter from Lewitt)
  - Robert Lobe, 1992-1994 (Box 6, Folder 16-18)
    (Includes 5 letters from Lobe)
  - Robert Mangold, 1973-1985 (Box 6, Folder 19-21)
    (Includes a letter from Mangold)
  - Christian Marclay, 1987-1992 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - John Margolies, 1977-1987 (Box 6, Folder 23-25)
    (Includes a letter from Margolies)
  - Gregg Morris, 1986-1988 (Box 6, Folder 26)
    (Includes a letter from Morris)
  - Peter Nagy, 1985-1987 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Manuel Neri, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Tom Otterness, 1983-1996 (Box 6, Folder 29-35)
  - Michael Paha, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Judy Pfaff, 1980-1993 (Box 6, Folder 37-38)
  - Don Porcaro, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Martin Puryear, 1974-1992 (Box 6, Folder 40-44)
  - Martin Puryear, continued, 1974-1922 (Box 7, Folder 1-14)
  - Robert Rauschenberg, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - James Rosenquist, 1973-1978 (Box 7, Folder 16-17)
  - Jim Sanborn, 1990-1995 (Box 7, Folder 18-22)
  - Lisa Scheer, 1987-1995 (Box 7, Folder 23-27)
    (Includes a letter from Scheer)
  - Sean Scully, 1973-1995 (Box 7, Folder 28-33)
    (Includes 4 letters from Scully and 2 color transparencies of Scully and an installation)
  - Joel Shapiro, 1976-1977 (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - Cindy Sherman, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 35)
  - Martin Silverman, 1983-1995 (Box 7, Folder 36-38)
    (Including 3 letters from Silverman)
  - Ned Smyth, 1977-1985 (Box 8, Folder 1-4)
  - Joan Snyder, 1977-1994 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Alan Sonfist, 1988-1995 (Box 8, Folder 6-10)
    (Includes 3 letters from Sonfist)
  - Pat Steir, 1978-1990 (Box 8, Folder 11-16)
  - Frank Stella, 1973-1976 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Donald Sultan, 1986-1990 (Box 8, Folder 18-19)
  - John Torreano, 1984-1993 (Box 8, Folder 20-23)
    (Includes 3 letters from Torreano)
  - Michael Tracy, 1982-1989 (Box 8, Folder 24-26)
    (Includes 4 letters from Tracy)
  - Anne Truitt, 1974-1994 (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Andy Warhol, 1972-1991 (Box 8, Folder 28-30)
  - Andrea Way, 1985-1994 (Box 8, Folder 31)
    (Includes a letter from Way)
  - Leslie Wayne, 1992-1994 (Box 8, Folder 32)
  - William Wegman, 1979-1995 (Box 8, Folder 33-36)
  - William Wegman continued, 1979-1995 (Box 9, Folder 1-5)
  - Tom Wesselmann, 1983-1991 (Box 9, Folder 6-10)
    (Including 2 letters from Wesselmann)
  - Isaac Witkin, 1981-1993 (Box 9, Folder 11-14)
  - Brian Wood, 1979-1992 (Box 9, Folder 15-17)
  - Elizabeth (Betty) Abrahams Woodman, 1986-1992 (Box 9, Folder 18-20)
  - Robert Zakanitch, 1979-1994 (Box 9, Folder 21-26)
    (Includes 2 color transparencies of studio)
  - Jose Zaragoza, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 27)
    (includes a letter from Zaragoza)
  - Joe Zucker, 1976-1994 (Box 9, Folder 28-31)
- Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1993-1994; Series 4; (1 folder)
  This series consists of one file containing two brochures concerning the K&B Corporate collection in New Orleans, Louisiana, and two copies of Editions Report.
  - Brochures and Editions Report (1993-1994), 1993-1994, undated (Box 9, Folder 32)